<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on Mike&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/tags/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on Mike&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 21:49:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CTF Forensics Field Guide</title>
      <link>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/ctf-forensics-field-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 21:49:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/ctf-forensics-field-guide/</guid>
      <description>Note: this post was also submitted as a chapter to the CTF field guide.
Forensics In a CTF context, &amp;ldquo;Forensics&amp;rdquo; challenges can include file format analysis, steganography, memory dump analysis, or network packet capture analysis. Any challenge to examine and process a hidden piece of information out of static data files (as opposed to executable programs or remote servers) could be considered a Forensics challenge (unless it involves cryptography, in which case it probably belongs in the Crypto category).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Look at the Rust Programming Language</title>
      <link>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/a-tour-of-rust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 13:06:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/a-tour-of-rust/</guid>
      <description>Where to Find More Execution Performance Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law is just about done. It once described a trend of transistor count doubling every 24 months (enabled by increasing the density of transistors by making them ever-smaller). Now:
 Between the introduction of 65 nm and 45 nm chips, about 23 months passed. To get from 45 nm to 32 nm took about 27 months, 28 months to go down from there to 22 nm and 30 months to shrink to the current 14 nm process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enigma2017 CTF Overflowme Writeup</title>
      <link>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/enigma2017-overflowme-writeup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 17:52:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/enigma2017-overflowme-writeup/</guid>
      <description>As mentioned in my last post, I spent some time solving security challenges posted on HackCenter for the Enigma2017 conference. This one (obviously) was to exploit a buffer overflow vulnerability. It was meant to be relatively easy, but sometimes you don&amp;rsquo;t realize the easiest approach first. I&amp;rsquo;ll walk through not just the solution, but the things I tried that didn&amp;rsquo;t work. It was a refresher course in exploitation for me – I&amp;rsquo;ve spent many years on defense research and needed to brush up again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Blog in 2017</title>
      <link>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/static-site-generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 15:43:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/post/static-site-generators/</guid>
      <description>My first blog, back in the early 2000s, was on a hosted blogging platform known as Blogger. It was simple and convenient: as the admin you just logged into the Blogger service, edited posts in your browser, and hit publish. This is basically how Tumblr still works today, although Tumblr&amp;rsquo;s innovation was to include media file hosting and allow everyone to repost each others&amp;rsquo; content.
But Blogger content was static, and textual.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>